<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gianluca Aguzzi on Danilo Pianini</title>
    <link>https://danysk.github.io/designs/gianluca-aguzzi/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Gianluca Aguzzi on Danilo Pianini</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© Danilo Pianini</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://danysk.github.io/designs/gianluca-aguzzi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Field-Based Approach for Runtime Replanning in Swarm Robotics Missions</title>
      <link>https://danysk.github.io/portfolio/2025-acsos-swarm-replanning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://danysk.github.io/portfolio/2025-acsos-swarm-replanning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;🏆 &lt;strong&gt;Best Student Paper — ACSOS 2025&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ensuring mission success for multi-robot systems operating in unpredictable environments&#xA;requires robust mechanisms to react to unpredictable events,&#xA;such as robot failures, by adapting plans in real-time.&#xA;Adaptive mechanisms are especially needed for large teams deployed in areas with unreliable network infrastructure,&#xA;for which centralised control is impractical and where network segmentation is frequent.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This work advances the state of the art by proposing a field-based runtime replanning approach&#xA;grounded in aggregate programming.&#xA;Through this paradigm,&#xA;the mission and the environment are represented by continuously evolving fields,&#xA;enabling robots to make decentralised decisions and collectively adapt the ongoing plan.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Demonstrator for Self-organizing Robot Teams</title>
      <link>https://danysk.github.io/portfolio/2025-coordination-robot-demo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://danysk.github.io/portfolio/2025-coordination-robot-demo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Self-organising multi-robot systems hold great promise for tackling complex tasks in&#xA;unstructured and dynamic environments,&#xA;yet bridging the gap between theoretical models and practical deployments remains challenging.&#xA;In this work, we present a demonstrator showcasing a team of robots that collectively&#xA;self-organise their behaviour using aggregate computing.&#xA;The demonstrator illustrates how high-level, globally-specified collective behaviour&#xA;can be automatically mapped to individual robot actions,&#xA;supporting coordination patterns such as leader election, coverage, and formation control.&#xA;The system is implemented on physical hardware and is also reproducible in simulation,&#xA;making it a concrete testbed for collective adaptive robotics research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Software Engineering for Collective Cyber-Physical Ecosystems</title>
      <link>https://danysk.github.io/portfolio/2025-tosem-collective-cps/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://danysk.github.io/portfolio/2025-tosem-collective-cps/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s distributed and pervasive computing addresses large-scale cyber-physical ecosystems,&#xA;characterised by dense and large networks of devices capable of computation, communication&#xA;and interaction with the environment and people.&#xA;While most research focusses on treating these systems as &amp;ldquo;composites&amp;rdquo;&#xA;(i.e., heterogeneous functional complexes),&#xA;recent developments in fields such as self-organising systems and swarm robotics&#xA;have opened up a complementary perspective:&#xA;treating systems as &amp;ldquo;collectives&amp;rdquo;&#xA;(i.e., uniform, collaborative, and self-organising groups of entities).&#xA;This article explores the motivations, state of the art, and implications of this&#xA;&amp;ldquo;collective computing paradigm&amp;rdquo; in software engineering,&#xA;discusses its peculiar challenges, and outlines a path for future research,&#xA;touching on aspects such as macroprogramming, collective intelligence,&#xA;self-adaptive middleware, learning, synthesis,&#xA;and experimentation of collective behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Decentralization Domains for the Internet of Things</title>
      <link>https://danysk.github.io/portfolio/2022-ieeeinternetcomp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://danysk.github.io/portfolio/2022-ieeeinternetcomp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Internet of Things (IoT) and edge computing are fostering a future of ecosystems hosting complex decentralized computations that are deeply integrated with our very dynamic environments. Digitalized buildings, communities of people, and cities will be the next-generation “hardwarae and platform,” counting myriads of interconnected devices, on top of which intrinsically distributed computational processes will run and self-organize. They will spontaneously spawn, diffuse to pertinent logical/physical regions, cooperate and compete, opportunistically summon required resources, collect and analyze data, compute results, trigger distributed actions, and eventually decay. What would a programming model for such ecosystems look like? Based on research findings on self-adaptive/self-organizing systems, this article proposes design abstractions based on “dynamic decentralization domains”: regions of space opportunistically formed to support situated recognition and action. We embody the approach into a Scala application program interface (API) enacting distributed execution and show its applicability in a case study of environmental monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
