<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Roberto Casadei on Danilo Pianini</title>
    <link>https://danysk.github.io/designs/roberto-casadei/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Roberto Casadei on Danilo Pianini</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>© Danilo Pianini</copyright><atom:link href="https://danysk.github.io/designs/roberto-casadei/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>From distributed coordination to field calculus and aggregate computing</title>
      <link>https://danysk.github.io/portfolio/2013-jos-alchemist/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://danysk.github.io/portfolio/2013-jos-alchemist/</guid>
      <description>Aggregate computing is an emerging approach to the engineering of complex coordination for distributed systems, based on viewing system interactions in terms of information propagating through collectives of devices, rather than in terms of individual devices and their interaction with their peers and environment. The foundation of this approach is the distillation of a number of prior approaches, both formal and pragmatic, proposed under the umbrella of field-based coordination, and culminating into the field calculus, a universal functional programming model for the specification and composition of collective behaviours with equivalent local and aggregate semantics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Partitioned integration and coordination via the self-organising coordination regions pattern</title>
      <link>https://danysk.github.io/portfolio/2020-fgcs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://danysk.github.io/portfolio/2020-fgcs/</guid>
      <description>Highlights Self-organising Coordination Regions (SCR) is a design pattern for decentralised self-integration in dynamic environments. SCR captures recurrent design approaches in a variety of domains including swarm control, resource management, and service orchestration. SCR consists of a dynamic process involving leader election, coalition formation, and feedback loops between leaders and subordinates. SCR can be straightforwardly implemented as continuous collective workflows in Aggregate Programming languages. SCR is versatile, as shown through case studies in edge computing and hierarchical, heterogeneous networks.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
